I'm a Senior in High School
Instead of taking the Korean SAT,
I took an exam to study abroad.
To study abroad?
(Questioner) Yes
I unfortunately failed
to pass the exam,
so I'm planning on studying
for another year
Many friends have passed the exam
without putting in as much effort into
studying as I have.
Now that I see this happen,
I'm starting to doubt the saying,
"You reap what you sow."
Hence I'd like to seek your thoughts.
I see.
If you look at life as a whole,
it moves by inevitable consequences.
That is, if you look at the big picture,
and you look long term.
Now when it comes to individual moments,
coincidences happen.
What do I mean by this?
To give an example,
if you plant a bean seed,
will it sprout or not?
(Questioner) It will sprout.
Right?
If it sprouts, would it not mean
that there was a bean seed there?
Please speak closer to the microphone.
I would mean that a bean was there.
Yes, it would
The bean seed is the 'cause' and
the sprout is the 'effect.'
If there's a cause, there's an effect.
We can also say that
there is no result without a cause.
Having said that, conditions apply. You
should have planted the bean seed in soil.
If you plant a seed in fire,
would it sprout?
(Questioner) It wouldn't.
It wouldn't.
If the bean spouted,
it's because there was a seed as a cause.
Cause led to an effect.
This is an inevitable consequence.
And yet not all beans sprout.
Coincidences intervene here
Do you understand?
If you study hard,
you'll get good results.
This is an inevitable consequence.
And yet you don't always get good results
on every exam by doing so
Right?
Who do you think will get good results?
Students who study hard,
or those who don't?
(Questioner) The ones who study hard would
That is an inevitable consequence.
The cause and effect is clear.
But sometimes you get a good score
even if you didn't study hard.
Sometimes you study very hard
but end up with a bad score.
When we consider certain athletes as good,
they should be winning all the time.
Right?
But they don't always
win every match, do they?
(Questioner) They don't.
They lose sometimes.
If you practice more than others,
you can run faster than others
And yet will you get
the same record every time?
Or will records vary depending
on your daily condition?
(Questioner) Records would vary.
Right?
Did you see the fastest runner
getting disqualified
at during the Daegu tournament?
(Questioner) No, I didn't.
You didn't?
I don't know his name,
but the fastest person
got disqualified for a false start.
He was unlucky, no?
(Audience Laughter)
And yet that is life.
Do you understand?
(Questioner) I do.
When you look at the bigger picture,
it isn't that big of a deal.
Do you understand?
Failing to pass this time may feel like
a huge difference from passing the exam
But when you look back
at the age of 60,
an extra year of studies won't
make much difference.
Whether you passed or not this time
isn't that important.
And yet it feels like a big deal to you
at this very moment in time.
Do you understand?
I'd recommend not taking a year off
if possible though.
(Audience Laughter)
Reason being -
it's not worth investing.
What you're studying now
isn't worth investing another year.
If it's worth it, it would be okay
to spend two years, three years off.
And yet your studies aren't worth it.
When society was centered
around educational backgrounds,
it made sense to study more.
While it may remain to an extent,
educational backgrounds won't be
as important going forward.
Your actual competence
will be more important.
An old lady's skill to make
the best Kimchi will be more valuable
than any Ivy League diploma.
And yet we haven't appreciated
the value of such skillsets until now.
We had considered a good degree
as most valuable.
This will be unlikely going forward
It's all about competence now.
Your actual ability is what counts.
Given we now live in such times,
don't try to make up on studying
by taking a year off.
It's possible that you may fail again
next year, is it not?
(Questioner) It's possible.
Yes, it is.
Then you would've just wasted your time.
My advice would be to go to
any college and study hard.
In other countries,
students take it easy in high school,
and then study really hard in college.
In Korea, students study really hard
until high school,
then they enjoy themselves in college,
So don't worry about college rankings
and go to a college that
suits your interests.
If you put the same effort into college
as you would've done studying
for another year,
would you not rank number 1 in college?
You would, would you not?
It's better to rank number 1 at UCLA
than to rank lowest of the class
at Harvard, so to speak.
So I hope you will change
your way of thinking.
I'm glad you asked the question.
And that is my advice to you.
Now does this mean that taking a year off
to study is absolutely unnecessary?
Not necessarily.
If you truly want to take a year off
to attend the school of your dreams,
you should.
Do you understand?
This would mean
you would be delayed by a year
And yet a year is nothing thinking
from a 60 year lifespan.
Ask anyone from your father's generation
Taking an extra year does not
make much of a difference.
There were people that
got into prestigious universities
and passed the bar during college.
Many were kicked out of school for
participating in protests,
fighting for labor rights, etc.
And yet after democratization,
those who were imprisoned became heroes.
They could even get far ahead of others
in when engaging in politics.
I'm saying that none of it really matters.
What matters is that you work hard
in whatever you do.
So taking a year off
to study is not an issue
Hence you shouldn't
stress over it too much
If you're thinking, 'I'm so unlucky.
That friend of mine is
already in college having fun.'
you are better off not
taking a year off.
Regardless of luck,
aren't there more things left
to study from high school?
(Questioner)
Not really
There aren't?
Then you should quit.
If you think there's nothing left to learn
from studying, you should quit.
If there's more to learn aside from
retaking the exam,
you should study hard.
Ask me anything more
What are you going to do?
Will you try another year?
Or will you go to a regular college?
I'm going to try one more time.
Then try one more time wholeheartedly.
Assuming you fail once again,
what will you do then?
I'll think more about it then.
You shouldn't think more about it.
Whatever happens,
you should consider this the last time.
Do you understand?
I personally think it's a waste of time
to try again even this round
While trying once more is fine,
you shouldn't try twice
Do you know of those slot machines
in Las Vegas?
You keep putting money in,
again and again
until you end up selling your house.
That's how you go bankrupt.
You should only try once for fun.
If you win, that's great.
If you don't, you don't.
That's how you should live.
Do you understand?
I do.
This is your one and only opportunity.
Should you study hard or not?
I should study hard
You're right.
Don't think of a next time.
There is no next time.
Why not?
Because it isn't worth it.
It isn't worthy of trying that many times.
Thank you.
(Audience Applause)